a way I think it is the central call and
invitation of all of these conversations
at least that I've been having is to be
like look you are alive this is your
chance what you do matters participate
participate in your life participate in
the world like that is it because
there's so many there's so much of our
system that is hell-bent on making us
forget that we are participants
to think that we're consumers or voters
something else we own our disciplines
here on this world and we can make a
sacred world where we can live in a flat
world or we can live in a materialist
world we get to participate in that in
any case
hello and welcome to the next episode of
voice club my name is Tim Adeline and
this is a conversation with Daniel
Thorson Daniel is the host of the emerge
podcast which has become a really really
pivotal podcast I think for collating a
whole range of really interesting
thinkers it tracks the themes of
civilizational collapse and what we can
do about that from the point of
civilization design but importantly it
also brings that element of personal
transformation how we can transform
ourselves and in so doing transform the
world it's not looking at it from an
either/or perspective it's very much
from a mode of we are deeply involved in
the world and how we develop ourselves
is also inherently related to the
systems we interact with and also
therefore how we can make the world you
know I'm not making that point
particularly well there that's not what
this introduction is about suffice to
say that's a way of thinking that also
resonates strongly with this project and
ultimately with the philosophical
outlook that underlies some of our
exploration here and also many of the
conversations in this project
now there are two parts to this
conversation and the first part is sort
mostly an outside-in look at what
Daniels taken to emerge so far on his
podcast inquiry which i think is really
interesting but but the second part is
to me even more interesting it certainly
felt that way to engage in it's much
closer to the core impulse of this
project which is to really engage in
transformative conversations perhaps
those from an inside out perspective
really feeling your way into a
philosophical exploration we talked
about Omni win and how to understand its
how to understand it whether or not it
should in fact be understood as an omni
growth way of conceptualizing systems
interaction you know when is it
appropriate to lose is it a good thing
to
we also talk about soul making and the
deep importance of participation but
most of all it's a dialogue that flowed
and one that well I hope I hope I hope
you find interesting and I hope actually
that it can be inspirational to some of
you who are looking to involve yourself
more in in the world but from a
perspective where you can do so really
grounded in yourself and there's a lot
to say there but in a certain mode of
listening and in a certain mode of
expression in a relationship self seems
to reveal itself reveals itself other
ways to but can be a beautiful thing and
yes
so Daniel introduces himself shortly he
lives in a monastery it's called their
monastic Academy it's based in Vermont
and fundamentally the monastic Academy
and as Daniel describes it is as they
describe their own mission is for the
preservation of life on Earth which is
which is a an exceptionally heavy load
and seems to me necessary it's a big
thing to sit with so yeah I will see you
very shortly
whether you're watching on YouTube or
listening as a podcast remember to
subscribe and hit the bell to track
upcoming releases myself alright Daniel
Thorson thank you so much for for being
here and entering into this conversation
with me yeah pleasure to speak with you
I've really enjoyed our conversations
yeah I have been following your work for
I think possibly around around about a
year give or take a few months I think
all of a sudden things start to blur a
little bit when it comes to tracking so
many of the elements within some sort of
subculture that I think we share a
mutual interest in certainly you are to
me a really key player in bringing
together really interesting voices and
adding to the discussion in a meaningful
way and what I'm hoping today to talk
about is what you see that discussion as
like how you've seen it emerge of course
your podcast is called emerge and so
perhaps you know if you could take a few
moments just to introduce yourself
briefly and then also talk about what
you're doing and then we can go into
perhaps what you see emerging yeah okay
sure so yeah I guess the the short kind
of current bio is as he said I host a
podcast called emerge it's been going on
for about two and a half years or so
although I took a little break in there
somewhere and I also live at a place
called the monastic Academy where I
train full-time in a kind of monastic ly
inspired training center where we spend
a lot of time and silent meditation we
do a practice called circling we do
trauma healing we do personal like peer
coaching and here I'm doing that
training and then I'm also helping
design a new curriculum
attempting to kind of ground some of the
ideas I've been exploring on my podcast
into an educational context and try to
train people for the kind of world that
I think both you and I sort of hope is
coming see coming you know what I want
to help nudge into being right that's
kind of the short bio and then the yeah
the podcast man it's hard to say what it
is I think you know I started it because
there were certain conversations that I
wanted to hear I've always listened to
podcast or like you know much of my
adult life it's been a major way that
I've learned and I've kept waiting for
certain conversations that mentioned I
was like oh maybe I'm I can have them to
be on the 1 to have them so I started
having them and really it was the reason
I chose the word emerge as the title is
because I wanted a brand that was broad
enough to include anything that I was
interested in mm-hmm
cuz being a friend of mine become almost
like victimized by his brand because he
used it to explore something that he's
really passionate about at the time but
then kind of fell out of love with and
it was really difficult for him and so I
basically used as an excuse to just talk
to people about what I was interested in
and just kept following that thread
following that thread and yeah so I've
had lots of really interesting
conversations around diversity of topics
many of which I think you're exploring
on your podcast as well and have found
my way into this weird little subculture
that yeah as you acknowledged like we
both kind of find ourselves in as ya
begin perform yeah yeah I can certainly
relate to wanting to have a broad enough
scope so that you can be free to follow
what's relevant as it comes up what
struck me then is you were talking
actually is yes what's emerging is so
interesting and that gives you the scope
but a key thing that you often discuss
is sort of what occurs before emergence
often and that's sort of decomposition
true and so it's got that it's got that
part-2 it - how would you describe the
environment or what sort of conversation
were you looking for that just wasn't
occurring
hmm yeah III I don't I don't know that I
could articulate it originally really it
was following a felt sense some kind of
desire some kind of like euros in
relationship to certain types of
conversation and as you say like when I
described there were some college
students here for a retreat this last
weekend and I was asked in front of them
like to describe what my podcast is
about and I don't know where they're all
from you know they're college students
they're kind of ideal ideological
commitments or whatever and I just said
the podcast the kind of thesis of the
podcast is something like or inquiry of
the podcast is something like the world
is falling apart what are we going to do
that's and that's really kind of it
right that's sort of the idea is that
there is this disintegration that's
falling apart the senescence of so many
of the aspects of the world that I think
for a long time we've taken for granted
or I mean out a long time you know
cosmically but you know in recent
history and and that is both needs to be
acknowledged right we need to
acknowledge that dissolution but also
see that you as you say it clears a
space for something new to emerge and
kind of trying to sort of sniff out the
the pheromones of that emergence as it's
occurring live on this planet right now
yeah partly as a hope - it's just to see
it but then also perhaps to kind of
facilitate its unfolding right at least
to be in touch with it so that you can
orient in a way that is authentic and
for some in the direction of love right
and that's and that's true - right like
it's like it's a little bit like I said
like I'm following what's emerging you
know but also like what's emerging is
like the alt-right and the rise of
authoritarian governments but I'm not
really covering that I'm not trying to
focus on that I have some kind of moral
commitment that colors and isolates
constrains my inquiry as you say and it
has to do with yet wanting to build
future that we can actually be proud to
live in yeah yeah how what what are the
key themes what are the elements of
conversation that either surprised you
that emerged or that were in fact they
sort of felt congruent with that initial
felt sense of inquiry and have now
become sort of really not concrete but
you know close to concrete pillars of
how you describe the the pheromones as
you said of what is substantial to use
as a basis for inquiry yeah yeah so the
I like the way you put that yeah it's
nothing that I didn't feel was there at
the beginning but they've all kind of
filled out right and so there's things
like the centralized
government's governance like whether
it's distributed autonomous
organizations or even things like in
spiral or holacracy and sort of the
emerging technology that might allow
those to scale their systems science
complexity science and in particular the
ability to kind of see things in terms
of flows that move in different ways are
constrained by different factors one
thing that actually has kind of
surprised me is for me that the inquiry
around the importance of soul and
soulfulness and soul making that wasn't
really on my radar before that of course
like the kind of relevance and
significance of personal development and
personal transformation in terms of how
we can collectively meet the meta-crisis
and then you know different flavors of
the meaning crisis as John for Vicki
talks about it I've kind of broached
that in a number of different ways right
and then another theme is of course like
kind of a
a letting go of the world that we've
grown up with and the stories and like
kind of narratives about what our lives
ought to be that civilizational
operating-system
gave to us which has been for me very
painful and like a long process yeah and
yeah I'm sure there are others that's
just kind of like some hood my head I
mean we've also explored meta modernism
and yeah like integral and all that kind
of weird stuff yeah it's interesting the
different communities different memes
hmm that are clustered around whatever
that broad area of inquiry is that you
just articulated if I was to put it into
slightly other words and I'm sure I'm
leaving out crucial parts of it but it's
something like how do we put together
synthesize or or relate in a congruent
fluid way the inner development and
expression of individuality in a
landscape of interconnection where we
ourselves are complex agents having an
effect on a complex multi-layered world
so ha and the meaning associated with
what it is to express our authentic
unfolding and evolution in that larger
dynamic that itself is changing and so
there's something quite meta about that
and so there is this meta element that I
think sort of ties together a lot of
these different communities whether you
know the meta modernists which I'm not
too familiar with although I do try to
track it a bit or
of course you have you know those
awesome cofounders of the neuro hacker
collective just trailblazing what
they're doing
providing meta map after meta map and
and Jordan Peterson actually as well was
he was you know his intellectual
scaffolding was a meta theory of meaning
and of course the integral theorists the
same and so there is this sense in which
you know putting a sort of trying to
find some fertile center ground as in
some sense not on the same plane but
raised something that is able to offer a
perspective that is perhaps beyond
dichotomies that are tired and not
serving us and that move towards
transcending and including then
obviously with the with the famous
integral phrase is a sort of basic
scaffolding for transformation in
general so there is somewhere that I
think would be interesting to for us to
try and explore together and I want to
see if I can set the stage for it it's I
hope I can I hope I can express the idea
well enough so the idea I mean I might
begin by saying like we're embedded in
an interrelation of complex systems and
some change quicker than others you know
obviously our cells have a shorter life
span and neurons and we have we live for
so long cities lasts for so long
generally speaking government
civilizations the solar system species
and there's a sense in which what is
meaningful is to engage in a certain
kind of loving transformation towards
some sort of how we say
stability but also expression over time
some sort of fulfillment some sort of
hole-making of one's own individual self
in relationship to others all the time
while elements of yourself and the world
around you are moving at various cycles
towards decay and it's perhaps a a task
especially in the world that we wake up
to right now which is one where we have
the capacity at least to some degree to
reflect and to engage in abstraction and
to watch this crazy dynamic of
witnessing and being with and
participating and then being
disconnected so that we can in some
sense take a perspective and and that's
something really worth talking about
but the idea might be how do we so an
interesting Avenue for exploration is at
what level or which problems or which
underlying systemic changes or which
aspects of ourself are most in need of
tending and shepherding a certain
transformation as their time is right
rather than before their time some
things might serve us still for longer
there might be social aspects of our
society now that we might come to see in
a few hundred years time our you know
not not serving us then but right now
perhaps we're unaware of them or perhaps
that's not the right place for someone's
focus we've noticed obviously the
development of a certain morality over
time and it seems inappropriate to look
back at ancestors and just tar them all
with a brush of being absolutely immoral
there was a sense in which everyone was
responding to the dynamics of the time
and the incentives of the time with the
capacity they had in that and so
it becomes then crucial to consider just
what of our nature is most in need of
change and where I see this question
being relevant is when it comes to the
kind of conversation and the kind of
points that let's say Daniels Martin
burger raises and that have become key
parts of the emerging conversation which
is to do I suppose with rival risk
dynamics and a certain win lose attitude
towards how we show up in the world in
relationship with others and that's and
that is deep it's so deep and I'm not
sure how deep I add I actually don't
know how deep it might be so deep that
that is all there is I like it gets so
deep where I'm like okay how at what
level is this picked apart where where
do we go to find ourselves in that and
and so you know I began by saying with
this question I hope I composed it
probably I don't have a full articulated
question I've tried to give a context of
some things changing quickly and some
things changing slowly and to be a sort
of as elegant as possible about changing
things but we're at this point where
things need to change in huge ways
because consequences are so drastic so I
wonder what comes up for you there in
terms of perhaps where you found some of
the most fundamental underlying the sort
of the deep code the deep programs that
you feel are worthy to draw up into
articulation as those that we ought take
seriously from a point of real
transformation
that's a beautiful question
I think I think over one of the pieces
of what you said that was most striking
was kind of this question of what if its
rival risk dynamics all the way down
and that's a really significant question
and a lot actually hinges on that on
that question and I think we you can
kind of put it put a bookmark in it but
just to say like the perspective of my
opinion but the buddha-dharma
and certainly the teacher here at the
monastery is that in fact there is we
might say like an omni Wynne foundation
to consciousness that is kind of waiting
to be overturned underneath the rival
risk at least that's how kind of I under
stand it yeah and so that's important to
eat least imagine that might be true for
any of us to actually work out in long
run in terms of like what needs to be
transformed I mean as you say it's so
hard to point to anything in particular
and I think that is why like Jordan and
Daniel really emphasized this capacity
for sovereignty and choice making right
because if you try to learn or unlearn
anything in particular it's connected to
everything else because everything is
connected and so you just don't know
kind of what you're doing that's kind of
how we got in the mess were in right
like we didn't know when we made cars to
solve the the horseshit problem in
cities and go faster that it would lead
to war in the Middle East and climate
change and so like we also have to what
we can do though is take a look at if we
can find it that which when increased or
when work done like allows us to then
respond skillfully in whatever
circumstances we find ourselves in
knowing that we don't know and
everything is changing so quickly that
certainly for me like what I really try
to like focus on is increasing my
sovereignty focusing on those capacities
of choice making
but yeah I don't really feel satisfied
with that answer given given the kind of
quality that I felt with your your
question yeah
what comes to mind for me is that the
question I asked is perhaps not the sort
of question that the feeling of so the
total satisfaction in answering it would
be appropriate right because it's it's
precisely the kind of question that
collective intelligence
let's hope is capable of addressing in
an ongoing fashion it's so challenging
because letting go of things is so
difficult yeah well and that's the other
thing that comes to mind is if you're
gonna work work on one thing I would say
come to terms with your own death mm-hmm
except that you will die mm-hmm not only
will that prepare you to be of service
but I think
the degree that we can make that
movement of accepting our own death we
can actually engage with this situation
we find ourselves and with our like
whole soul and our whole heart online
yeah like I was talking to Zach Stein I
was at I was recording an episode with
him yesterday and he said that you know
one way to look at this is that we can
put this soul as the as the basis as the
primary thing and then in that case
there are we might imagine that it would
be worse to lose your soul in the act of
saving the organic world then it would
be to let it pass and save your soul and
and nourish your soul protector so
obviously that's like a kind of like
extreme extreme position and it's not
like actually that's just to kind of
emphasize a point right and so like
that's something that I feel a lot too
is in this whole world this milieu it's
like oh we gotta like organize to save
the planet from collapse it's like well
like how are you treating your loved
ones right like what are your
conversations and relationships like
like what was the what's the what's the
health of your soul mmm how is it how is
it like as he said in the conversation
like that's the real game like game a
game be like yes please we need that but
also like don't forget you know yeah
something that I've found to be an
expression one of the expressions of a
bedrock place I found myself is the
expression I will not violate my soul
and that's non-negotiable yeah I can
detect that in being with you it's
actually a really like beautiful quality
that you have
and the link I see between what that
expression means or at least part of
what it means and conversation is but
there's a straight link there up into
the courage to step out and express what
seems resonant yes yeah and that seems
to be one key piece of wisdom throughout
the ages that underlies I think many of
the salient figures and speakers and
teachers of our time so and it's and it
accords with this fundamental truth of
the unique quality and importance of
every individual voice expression it
doesn't have to be verbal of course but
that there is a role that there is a
that there is a line of melody that
there is a part of the dance to
participate in and if that is brought
forth it it it's change is all I don't I
don't know what its changes but it is
involved yes yeah yes so there's
something I want to track back to and
draw up here and it relates back to this
interplay of rivalries dynamics and at
what layer of the psyche a collective
psyche perhaps biological substrate that
they're embedded in that it's embedded
in
and I you know it's funny on this side
of the conversation where I'm
experiencing myself for this moment as
putting the question forward it seems in
so doing I am carving the world in such
a way that leaves that is you know
somewhat oppositional that there is this
tension here and it's kind of breaking
things up so that then perhaps we can
move towards a witnessing or observing
and then that process becomes a cycle
that we can situate ourselves in as one
and therefore that julna s' that duality
perhaps perhaps you know becomes as one
and it's it's interesting that question
question a dynamic and the reason I say
it's because actually I'm in some deeper
sense that I can't express in the asking
of the question I believe and know that
at court due to the interconnected
nature of things that there is
inherently a equal parts beautiful and
tragic but ultimately a dynamic that is
transcendent of any sort of a final
win-lose formulation however situating
ourselves in relationship with that that
that that that nature that is there to
be with at times but I know for my part
I fall out of all the time and then our
actions in this plane at this time given
the complexity of them given our immense
power all of a sudden they're we're back
open again to this vast complexity but
what I have to say and what I hope I can
now now move myself along to to putting
forward is
that the wind lose dynamic as opposed to
the Omni win if that's characterized and
so I suppose first you know tell me if
this is a characterization you share if
this omni wind dynamic is perhaps a
instead of sort of an omni growth
dynamic then the idea of losing is
perfectly acceptable insofar as that
affords growth and continued
participation in a unifying feature that
is respected and loved as a cycle of
that loving participation for example so
I'm a I'm a big football fan soccer for
for you guys I support Tottenham fucking
best team in the world and and this a
domain in which I'm more than happy to
be motherfuckin rivalries okay mmm-hmm
right and and it's always there's always
that joke there and of course it's not
always that joke for some people and
then we can use that as a lens by which
to understand you know some people's
difficulty in life fundamentally but
there's a there's a there's something
still valuable about losing and this
there's referees and it's like okay we
we agree that there can only be one
winner but in the striving for that
there is a beautiful journey created and
we shake hands at the end and in some
sense there's a deeper there's a deeper
nature to the game that is there's a
beauty to it that is the true joy for me
for me and I think is the true joy that
underlies it so I suppose I'm asking you
how do you understand the Omni wind
dynamic and and
when is it appropriate to lose in some
sense or how what kind of losses are
important yeah I love that I love that
inquiry I mean so for me I think of Omni
win is this kind of like infinite game
attractor that we will almost certainly
like never realize right but it's useful
insofar as it helps us engage with the
world such that we start to see
opportunities for transformation mmm and
also get a kind of felt sense of like ah
this is the world that we want to create
together it's totally reasonable to me
that there could be like losing
it what looks like losing in the context
of a grander winning a richer winning
like that and that makes a lot of sense
to me and I think there's something that
was said in the new things called that
is it the Nordic ideology the second
book and listening society trilogy where
they say like really the one way another
way to understand is like we want to
make the losing less bad right
and so people there might still be like
winners and losers like I you know seems
like reasonable at least for many many
years into the future but like that
losing would turn you into a social
pariah where you're just put into
basically a hell realm on earth mmm due
to circumstances of birth or whatever
you know all the ways in which our
current system basically casts you out
exhales you from though like the kind of
benefits of being human right there's so
there's something in that like we want
to make the losing less bad but then
yeah totally like I mean even like you
know you I can imagine like a sports
context like there's this this this
something I want to climb and I try to
climb and I lose over and over again and
that's part of the journey of winning
right and so there is clearly like
developmentally this sort of movement of
challenge and failure and failure and
failure and then like rising to the
occasion and like certainly like here at
the monastery which I often think about
as a kind of like microcosm Omni win
system right all of us are here for the
sake of our growth there's a lot of like
losing going on in the sense that you
get you get told like you did that wrong
you did not do that well enough you lost
you you had a goal and you did not
achieve it you know and you Lobby
you know in a way that's a kind of
losing but is in service of a bigger
wing and a context that we can all kind
of trust in believe in feel a part of
mmm which I don't think can in any way
shape or form be said about the losing
that goes on
in our in our operating system
collectively right now so yeah I mean
that's kind of what comes up for me
ya know I think that all that all makes
a lot of sense when losing does not
afford or is not consistent with growing
or but and participating in the growth
and wholeness and whole making of the
collective then it's to me that seems
like a decent first crack at a
definition of the badness of losing that
does not serve anyone and that we do not
want to see yeah yeah yeah yeah and just
to make it less vicious so vicious in
the world today it's so vicious it's so
easy as well and look and I can only
speak to this from a from some blinkered
perspective what I have witnessed in my
own life is just how difficult it is to
make productive movements towards
betterment in any form when your key you
know physiology is fucked when your
nervous system is not in a good state
you know and these baseline conditions
it's it it does seem to be the case that
people forget or perhaps never have
experience but then forget just what it
is to be in a state of less capability
and yeah yeah this was something perhaps
I did not understand as well as I do now
I don't think I was majorly blind about
it but you know we take a certain you
know we have like a a minimum
Viable Product as a as a big organ and
if some of those conditions aren't met
then it's very very difficult to move
the needle in other places and really
yeah this is an example of the yeah yeah
III think we agree so wholeheartedly I
think it's you know I've been in states
of crippling like near suicidal
depression before right which has given
me a kind of I think a sense of what it
can be like to just have we might say
like a very reduced sovereignty right
like very little freedom very little
capacity to meet the world as it is
right it's like at least in America like
maybe most people maybe more than most
people are like locked in a state of
stress response that is compromising
their capacity as an organism to
actually do like coherent sense making
to really like make good choices like
and it's like yeah that's the state of
our world like in which losing puts you
in a position where you're subject to
negative feedback loops and make you
harder and harder and harder it's a
downward spiral of poverty and certainly
here in America it's a very real
phenomenon and it's it's terrifying so
what it means to like not lose so bad
with me but somehow we we break that
spiral we create a floor that people
can't lose past
that's just like like if when I say it
it feels so obvious but it's also
clearly hasn't been done and so it's
radical in a way you know sure sure and
well and of course we could talk about
incentives that people you know are in
an environment with that might affect
them to recognize this less and it's
also a capacity of awareness to attend
to what about your structure the
different elements of it are or are not
in a position where you yourself are
able to act with more sovereignty so I
suppose it takes so
20 to recognize a lack of it as well so
that we have always these both sides and
there was something that came up when
you were speaking speaking now which
ties in with some of them means I think
John Bevere key amongst others is most
like a the right figure to point to in
this emerging conversation things he's
introduced and a lot of the terms he's
introduced of course are from other
researchers and he's kind of collating
them and and so in my apologies for not
being educated enough to speak to the
appropriate you know people who have
introduced these terms but but you
mentioned negative feedback loops and
this is a key thing to realize that we
can get stuck in and this is you know a
good first approximation of addiction
John refers to it as a reciprocal
narrowing of the capacity to attend I
love that framing yeah yeah it's really
really nice whereas self-transcendence
being a reciprocal opening so as this
sense and it is you know the notion of
sovereignty is of course playing a role
in there is this capacity again to look
out observe sense make act observe again
discern of course so if we're looking
then at what is some kind of unifying
feature of society the collective which
enables losing good losing to contribute
then I mean it just struck me that it
that in itself a crucial
characterization of that unifying
feature needs itself to be open to its
own reciprocal opening its own
transcendence so what in fact we
participate in itself is itself open to
the same kind of transformation which
all of a sudden then but to to and that
concept is something I've been thinking
about for a long time and it's not an
easy concept I think to grasp although
I'm really terrible at telling what's
easy or not easy to grasp I'm hopeless
actually I'm hopeless
that and that's a major arrow of mine
it's almost selfish it's like once I
understand something I don't know I
don't understand how I understand it and
then I forget how I didn't notice how I
didn't understand it before that's
actually a particular kind of bias I
think it's like called the experts bias
or something like that it's like it's
right I'm in a fallacy I only learned
about it recently it's fast because I
have that same right I actually don't
know how to address that apart from in
dialogue with someone in dialogue with
someone then and you can attend where to
what self yeah yeah and as far as
disseminating a message without being in
touch with people yeah clearly I have
not a good grasp on this so yeah I I
feel that what also one thing I want to
say is I I feel very strongly like
philosophically totally aligned and
resonant with what I hear you expressing
right in the bike and there's this
beautiful book called Network ologies
which is a philosophy of networks it's
not like Network science it's actually
more like kind of like deluzy and
philosophy applied to networks and what
it posits as the very central function
of the kind of mmm networks there I mean
to put it licit like the networks that
are going to save the world right create
a context of robust emergence right
robust emergence means emergence the
emergence that we trust to go on and
continue right and just as such a simple
frame right but what we have right now
in our in our culture in our world is
emergence that is not robust that is
actually going to decline and as in
senescence and so what does it mean to
create robust emerges emergence that
actually begets itself in an auto poetic
way over and over again creating new
novelty new opportunities for growth new
understandings of what growth even is
because we probably don't even know what
it is human beings have not found the
farthest reaches of what a human being
can be you know look at what we have to
overcome if we're educated in most of
the you know public education system if
they're like first uninstall that before
we can even get to baseline like yeah
and so it's like yeah I think I really
vibe with that sort of flavor and
aesthetic of like what we're actually
going for is that like endless like
creation newness like emergence pouring
forth of the human soul back into itself
in order to reflect back out into the
world and this kind of like yeah
infinite process of soul making
collective soul making that's what it
points to for me and yeah there's
something I love about that it's hard to
see it's hard to see another all right
it's hard to all right I don't know it's
hard to be motivated by anything else I
would add another piece to it
which is that if we understand that
they're unfolding and evolving and that
you know continual making as a certain
kind of growth and there's a soil
there's a ground in which that growth is
embedded and is nourished from and this
gets back to this idea of something's
changing slowly and something's changing
quickly so it's the mechanisms we have
in fact to analyze well though it's not
just analysis that's doing it there's
still this capacity just to discern in
this other way that's oriented by this
feeling tone or we want to say it but
it's what it's yeah it's really what a
what what are the plate tectonics that
are supporting us now and what are the
what are the dead roots that need to
change always that recursive
self-reflective criticality and so we
are across the we are across the past
and the future right like we are
attendant to what is relevant in all of
it somehow so it's obviously not just an
expansion out without attachment and
love for its roots and it's what in our
roots is like what are we when we take
away or when we act from I what what
we'd reduce humanity down to like before
like what is there in our nature like oh
sorry I'm losing it here but it's this
dynamic between connection and
disconnection like what are we
disconnected from and what do we find
when we connect back to that and how
ubiquitous is that source of connection
or at what point yeah well what's what's
coming up for me as I hear you speak is
there's a kind of sense of you know this
this kind of oscillatory or both and
nature of going back and retrieving and
in some cases protecting that which has
brought us to this point well also
forward-looking kind of preparing to
move into totally different unknown
futures and that like there's I really
appreciate the that like one of the
proposed icons of the meta modern
movement is Janice the two-faced God
right who's looking back into the past
and also forward into the future
and kind of being there in the present
acknowledging the value in both
directions and not like leaning too far
forward or too far back and yeah it's
kind of finding that that that Center
we're not and I think that the my own
tendency and III yeah I suspect the
tendency of this kind of emerging
subculture is going to be leaning too
far into the future leaning too far
forward not doing the work it takes to
fully understand what you think you're
deconstructing and letting go of because
it takes a lot of work like in the
context of the Buddhist tradition you
know that I'm participating in here like
the amount of thinking and beautiful
sophisticated elegant like just
mind-blowing thoughtfulness that went
into the construction of this tradition
that we then like Westerners think we
can come in and be like ah like I wrote
a hundred page book and like this is
what Buddhism is about you know no need
for all of that that we thought we
needed like I got it you know it's that
the kind of like audacity of that and
the arrogance of that is really striking
and and I think that there are III
imagine because Buddhism is the kind of
system that I'm sort of closest with
that that's probably true for many many
many different systems arenas domains
disciplines that we are considering
moving beyond or considering
transcending and including without
actually doing the work of knowing what
it means to include that thing it's very
easy for transcending and including to
become a kind of way of bypassing and
ignoring something without actually
getting access to the understanding and
wisdom that is pointing to you know
that's very interesting that's very very
interesting I keep looking across just
to check the time but know that yeah I
what struck me is the importance of
dialogue and the importance of immediate
participatory feedback with others in an
attempt to make sense of things right
there's something about writing that is
a beautiful exercise I love it
it's extremely important to me I've
published nothing hmm and I've written a
lot I've published nothing I write to
myself I try to understand things and
develop my understanding and I'm
constantly faced with the inadequacy of
what I see in front of me to contribute
to where I feel actually most resonant
to then explore and question and I'm not
trying to make a more general point here
exactly other than I mean this is my own
experience but there's something there
is something about there's something
there's something attractive about you
know writing a book and exploring things
through and taking people on a journey
and having that stuff all down there but
you know we're not a life is not a
closed book mmm some things we can you
know look at and go okay you know this
is wrong but then there's still the
participating in that understanding of
what that was and it's something hi this
I'm so much more it feels more that
interaction that's what I'm so I'm so
grateful for all the different people
doing this out here in particular people
like John vivace who engaged so much
with so many people and this is someone
who has done has done the work to write
many books he has of course written a
bunch of things there's something he
still clearly so values and realizes as
important as a key part of his message
to involve yourself in the participation
of of understanding yeah I feel that
really strongly and you know as I've
become more associated with the whole
kind of meta space in general whether
it's meta modernism or integral and you
know now now folks reach out to me that
are just doing some kind of weird crazy
meta thing not to irregularly and they
want me to look at their really abstract
theory about systems and systems of
systems and how they all intersect and
make sense of the other systems and it's
like
for me so much of that is useful insofar
as it points you back to your life right
like so much of that I think is
masturbatory feels that way to me not
not all of it of course I love it I
engage in it yeah I'm great
me too but huh man like I think it's I
think it's an example of the lack it can
be so difficult to engage in
conversation about some of these things
and perhaps something we share is that
we both started a podcast in part I
think to have conversations it's to be
alright in it right yeah but yeah but I
think like as you say there's this word
this idea of participation for me like
it kind of cuts through all of the
abstractions mm-hmm so for in a way I
think it is the central call and
invitation of all of these conversations
at least that I've been having is to be
like look you are alive this is your
chance what you do matters participate
participate in your life participate in
the world like that is it because
there's so many there's so much of our
system that is hell-bent on making us
forget that we are participants
to think that we're consumers or voters
something else we are not anticipating
here on this world and we can make a
sacred world or we can live in a flat
world or we can live in the materialist
world we get to participate in that in
any case
think it's so essential I think John for
Vicki nails it in that yes that is it
that's the core of the core of the core
of the core yes yes yeah that's
beautiful Daniel yeah I really
appreciate your expression of that mmm I
recall and I can't say this is a direct
quote just because my mind is not good
at remembering direct quotes but
something John said once
the participation in the
self-transcending transformation of the
question and to do this and to
participation to participate of course
invokes the notion of relationship
invokes this notion of being in a
collective where the participation of
everyone is valued and it's transforming
transforming what's relevant in
community where the individual is valued
that is the that is this is what we have
to do
what I want to well that she that that
brings us right to that brings us right
to the end here but what I want to ask
you just in closing and this is
something I you know depending on how
the answer is something I could clip and
maybe put at the beginning just because
I want to offer you the opportunity to
direct people to maybe particular
episodes that you've published that you
think are really interesting for people
to engage with I'm conscious that the
conversations I have are often assuming
quite a bit of understanding and that
can make it I think difficult for people
who aren't you know exposed to any of
this stuff to necessarily be involved
and I find that some of the podcasts
you've released have got some really for
example and I'm just gonna say at the
Daniels Martin burger one I think this I
recommended this to loads of people is
just an excellent example of the kind of
the some of the bedrock some of the
important bedrock articulations of his
understanding of things that inform that
speak to what is emerging as resonant to
discuss so what would you direct people
to in specifically your own in your own
culture sure so I would say I would
listen to the episode I did with Ronan
Harrington I think that's a really good
introduction to what we might call like
the Nordic brand of meta modernism and
then yeah direct people to the Daniel
'shmock Tim burger which would be the
perhaps California flavor of meta
modernism and then honestly like because
there's this other thing that we've
talked about like about soul that I
don't think either of those
conversations really speak to but a
conversation like with bear and silver
which was earlier on and my catalog I
think would give that flavor and is a
beautiful beautiful one of my favorite
conversations really beautiful and so
yeah I guess that would be what comes to
mind beautiful well Daniel perhaps you
stick around for this one minute with
you know with me after this but thank
you so much for showing up and do a
little pleasure I really enjoyed this
exploration
whether you're watching on YouTube or
listening as a podcast remember to
subscribe and hit the bell to track
upcoming releases myself